Hi, everyone. My name is
Dr. Joseph Holloway, and in
this session, we're going
to be talking about the
bacterial and fungal causes
of infective endocarditis.
So here are the objectives
for the lecture today.
We're going to start with
some basic definitions and
classifications of
endocarditis, along with some of
the epidemiology and risk
factors associated with it.
From there, we'll move on to
more of the microbiological
aspects of the disease,
and we'll talk about
some of the common and
less common bacterial and
fungal causes of it, along
with the pathogenesis, some
of the microbial features
and virulence factors,
and then we'll also touch
on some of the laboratory
techniques that allow
you to identify and
diagnose the different
forms of endocarditis. So
what do we mean when we
say infective endocarditis?
Well, the first thing is
an infection, right? So
there have to be microbes
making their way into
the blood, whether those
are bacterial or fungal
microbes. And those microbes
are going to then cause
inflammation of the
endocardium, which is the
internal lining of the
heart. And that takes into
account the valves of the
heart as well. And it's
really the valves that are
going to be the location
where microbial colonization
is going to occur.
Now, endocarditis can
be subdivided into
two basic categories.
You have the
acute form of
endocarditis or subacute.
Now, for the acute
form, that can occur
to normal valves or it
could occur to abnormal
valves like you
see below, native
valves or something
like a prosthetic valve.
And acute form of
endocarditis is going to be
brought about by more
highly virulent organisms.
So, classically, Staph
aureus would be a cause for
acute endocarditis. And
because of that, it's going
to show a much more
virulent, rapid progression.
Patients are going to
have higher fevers,
and it's going to last
a shorter course, a
couple of days to weeks
to show the symptoms.
And that could be
compared to a subacute
form of endocarditis
where you have less
virulent organisms
causing the pathology.
And a good example of that
would be the commensal
oral flora causing the
subacute case of endocarditis.
And so because of that, you
get a slower progression
that lasts more in the time
period of weeks to even
months. You have patients
that have lower fevers.
And one other thing to
consider is intravenous drug
use. And that can lead to
a case of endocarditis as
well. Again, the typical
cause is going to be staph
aureus, and classically, it's
going to be associated with
the tricuspid valve on the
right side of the heart.
At this point, I think
it's instructive to
cover the basic pathogenesis
of endocarditis.
Now, the disease has to
occur in the background of
damaged endothelial
cells or damaged to the
endothelial lining of a valve.
And so what this will do
is it will expose
subendothelial matrix proteins.
At that point, serum
proteins and platelets
and fibrin have the
potential for aggregating
at that location and
creating a thrombus,
at which point you
would then consider this
to be non-bacterial
thrombotic endocarditis,
otherwise known as
morantic endocarditis.
Now, that's not something
that we're necessarily going
to talk about today, but it
does serve as the background
for infective endocarditis.
So you have this pre
-existing thrombus that's
sterile, and you add to that
transient microbes in the blood
that then have the potential
to also adhere to that
thrombus. Now, at that point,
you then have the bacteria
that are going to be
dividing. that is also going
to allow for the attachment
of different types of immune
proteins to that location,
to that thrombus, and the
addition of more serum proteins
and platelets. And what
this does is it produces a
large thrombus known as a
vegetation. So the vegetation
then has the ability to
obviously disrupt the tissue,
right? So you can get tissue
destruction based on the
growing vegetation at that
location. But the growing
vegetation is also then going
to disrupt the functionality
of the valve. And this is
where you get the valvular
regurgitation that's
associated with endocarditis.
Now, in addition to that,
as the vegetation is going
to grow, there is a potential
for little parts of that
vegetation to then break
off and enter into the
bloodstream. Now if that
happens on the right side of the
heart, which is certainly
less common, right, but that
has the ability then to
cause a pulmonary embolism.
Now on the left side of the
heart, the mitral valve for
instance, which is going
to be much more common, if
you have part of a vegetation
breaking off, you now
have an embolism that is entering
into systemic circulation.
And once that happens,
you have the potential for
that embolism really to go
anywhere, and that could
lead to many different
complications to endocarditis.
So who exactly is getting
endocarditis? What are the
risk factors and the
epidemiology associated with it?
So certainly age is one of
the biggest risk factors,
and that should make sense.
Obviously, as people age,
there's going to be more
of a need for some of those
individuals to have
prosthetic devices, prosthetic
valves, and so age becomes a
very important risk factor.
You can see that
most of the patients,
you know,
50 percent of the patients
that are going to have
endocarditis are going
to be over the age of 60.
IV drug use, which
we mentioned already,
is a big risk factor. Now, that
is something that's
kind of specific,
a very unique type of
endocarditis, but certainly
an important risk
factor to keep in mind.
Poor dentition or any
sort of oral manipulation
that's going to allow for
your oral flora, those
bacteria, to gain access
to the bloodstream. So that
would be an important risk
factor to keep in mind and
obviously anything that
has to do with your heart
in terms of previous
pathology previous history
of endocarditis maybe
rheumatic fever any sort of
structural issue that you
have with your heart you
know for instance a mitral
prolapse or any other sort
of cardiac issue an
implantable device, if you
have any sort of cardiac
surgery, which again can
allow for microbes to gain
access to the bloodstream,
these would all be risk
factors to keep in mind.
Now, given all those risk
factors, the incidence
of endocarditis is
relatively low, 15 out of 100
,000 in the U.S., but still
it could be very important
to identify, especially
in certain instances,
for instance, in an acute
form of endocarditis.
And as we mentioned,
age is going
to be one of the
key risk factors.
50% of the patients are going
to be over the age of 60.
Males are going to show
this more than females, and
that could be for a number
of reasons. Maybe males
are a little bit more prone
to having cardiac issues.
Maybe males have a
higher probability of
engaging in IV drug
use. So there's probably
a number of different
reasons why males
might show endocarditis
more than females.
And then lastly, the
cause of endocarditis,
the microbes that are
causing it, certainly
bacteria, are going
to be far more common
of a cause than a
fungal cause would be.
so having said that let's take
a look at the distribution
of microbial pathogens
that actually cause
infective endocarditis now
the first thing to say is
that you don't have to
memorize all these percentages
that you see on the screen
instead i think what's
important is that you take
a step back and what you
can see then is that the
main causes of IE are the
staphylococci, the streptococci,
and the anorococci.
Now of course it's important
also to identify the
minor causes both fungal
and bacterial and so moving
forward in the lecture what
we're going to be discussing
is how to be able to
identify a particular species
that might be causing the
infective endocarditis.
All right, so we'll
start here with the
Staphylococci group, which
is the most prevalent
cause of infective
endocarditis. It makes up
probably approximately
40% of all the cases.
Now, that takes into
account both Staphylococcus
aureus and Staphylococcus
epidermidis.
Both of those are going to
have some common features.
The first thing to
mention about them is that
they're both part of the
normal flora of humans.
So approximately 50% of
all people have Staph
aureus on their skins
or in their nasopharynx.
And as the name
would imply, Staph
epidermidis is one of
the most abundant and
common microbes of
the human skin flora.
So virtually
everybody has that.
Now to be categorized
as a Staphylococcus, the
first feature is that you
have to be a coccus-shaped
bacterial cell, so a
circular bacterial cell. And
those cells, as designated
by the term Staphylo,
they are going to range
themselves in clumps. And so
the clumps, irregular clumps,
basically are based on the
divisional plane of the
cells. They could divide in
any plane, and so that makes
the cells clump together
irregularly, classically
known as grape-like clusters.
So they will clump
together when seen under
a microscope, and
they're also all gram
positive after a gram
staining procedure.
Now importantly, the
staphylococci group are
catalase positive, and the
reason why that's important
is because that will
differentiate them from
the streptococci group,
which are commonly catalase
negative. So that's a
big way to differentiate
the two different genera,
one from the other.
Now, within the
staphylococcus group, we're
really focusing on staph
aureus and staph epidermidis
here. And so how
would you begin to
differentiate those? And
the first way to do that
is with a coagulase
test. And coagulase is an
enzyme that is secreted
from a bacterial cell,
and it's a very important
virulence factor. So
classically, staph aureus
is coagulase positive.
And what happens is the
enzyme is secreted into the
blood, and it will cause the
proteins in the blood plasma
to begin to clump together
or coagulate. And you
could even see that in the
image of the coagulase tubes.
So you see staph
epidermidis in one, staph
aureus in the other,
and staph epi is liquid,
whereas staph aureus
has produced a clot.
Now, what happens basically
is the enzyme coagulase
causes fibrinogen to
convert to fibrin, and
that will basically produce
a little clot around
the bacterial cells. And
so really the function
of that is to shield the
bacteria from the host
immune response and
basically to evade
surveillance from the host
immune cells and proteins.
Now, creating that
enzyme really is a point
of differentiation for
staph aureus and staph
epidermidis, so that's
one virulence factor.
Another virulence factor,
like you can see down
in the table, is the
creation of a biofilm.
Now, the biofilm is
really going to be brought
about by the production of
a capsule, which both of
these staph species are
going to be able to produce,
but they produce them
kind for different reasons
and they're constructed
a little bit differently
so for staph aureus the
capsule that it makes
again is really a defensive
mechanism to shield itself
from phagocytosis again
to evade the host immune
response very much like
the coagulase enzyme is
but the staph epidermidis
species will produce a
different variety of capsule
and that allows for the
adherence to different
substrates, and so it has a very
particular way of mediating
the creation of a biofilm
on different types of
indwelling devices like
prosthetic valves, and so you
have that type of virulence
factor associated with
staph epi, where you don't
necessarily have the biofilm
creation in Staph aureus.
All right, now, if
the coagulase test is
really the main way
that you differentiate
these two, if you
were to come across a
coagulase negative
type of Staph species,
what you can see there
then noted for Staph
epidermidis is that it's
Novobiasin sensitive.
So that would be another
test that you would
run on a coagulase
negative type of species.
and the reason for that
is to differentiate
Staph epi from another
very common Staph species
known as Staph
saprophyticus. And Staph
saprophyticus happens to
be novobiasin resistant, so
that's a very easy way
to differentiate any type
of Staph species that's
coagulates negative.
Now, differentiating Staph
species, you could also
do that, like you see in the
table, with the hemolytic
pattern that they produce.
So hemolysis is basically
brought about by, again,
the secretion of enzymes,
and those enzymes will
degrade red blood cells. So
when grown on a blood auger
plate, staph aureus will
produce enzymes that
degrade red blood cells
completely, which is known
as beta hemolysis, and that's
going to be different than
staph epidermidis, which
doesn't produce enzymes
and so is known as gamma
hemolysis or gamma hemolytic,
meaning that it does not
break down the red blood
cells at all. So it's
a different way that
you're just able to
differentiate the different
types of staph species.
Now, when you put
this all together,
what you could see is
that staph aureus then
with these different
types of virulence factors
is then the most common
cause, like you can
see down at the bottom
of the chart, the
most common cause of
acute endocarditis
and that's especially
true of iv drug users
so if you're going to inject
a needle into your arm
you now have a portal of
entry into the bloodstream
and of course staph
aureus is part or could be
part of the natural skin
flora and now has access
into the bloodstream and
that's going to be a little
bit different than staph
epidermidis which is more
aligned with subacute
cases, a little bit slower
progression where you have
the creation of a biofilm
on potentially a prosthetic
valve, which will
allow for the vegetation
to grow a little bit more
slowly. And so you see a
little bit slower of the
progress of the infective
endocarditis symptoms. All
right, so we'll
move on to a second
group of very
important microbes
that frequently cause
infective endocarditis and that
group is the streptococci
now you might notice that
included in the streptococci
group here is the enterococcus
genus and the reason
for that is that species
in the enterococcus genus
actually used to be many years
ago part of the streptococci
family. And for a
couple of detailed reasons,
they had subsequently been
separated into their own
genus, which is enterococcus.
So what we're going
to be doing is taking
a look at three
different examples
here, including the
enterococcus group.
Now, the streptococci
are going to be
differentiated from the
staphylococci that we just
talked about in a couple
of different ways.
Obviously, under a
microscope, we're going to
see gram-positive caucas
-shaped bacterial cells,
but the arrangement
of the cells is
going to be a little
bit different.
So where you would
expect to have clumps
and clusters in staph,
here in the strep group,
we would expect to
see chains of cells.
Now, that's fine
under a microscope,
but biochemically,
as I mentioned,
really the key is going
to be the catalase
test. where staph is going
to be catalase positive,
the strep family,
including enterococcus,
those are going to be
catalase negative. So
that's really a key
point of differentiation.
All right, now the first
example is going to be the
viridens group. So strep
viridens takes into account
a number of different
species, like you can see
represented in the chart.
So species like sanguinus,
mutans, mitus, those are
some representative species.
And if you fall into the
strep viridens group,
that is usually going
to place you into the
Lancefield group that
doesn't get a grouping.
And the Lancefield grouping
is based on antigenic
proteins that are found on
the surface of the cells. And
so some species fall nicely
into groups, group A,
group B, or group D, like
you see here, and others just
don't. And so if you don't
fall into a Lancefield
grouping, then you get lumped
into the viridens group.
Now, the majority
of viridens species
are going to be part
of the normal oral
flora that you would
find in a person.
And because that's the
location, the way that they
act in your oral cavity
is going to be the same
way that they're going
to act in producing a
vegetation on a abnormal
or disrupted heart valve.
All right, so the key to
the way that they operate
is by producing a polysaccharide
known as dextran. So
dextran is basically just
like a sticky sugar, and
in your oral cavity, that
sticky sugar that's being
produced by these different
species, that lays the
foundation for the biofilm
that we call dental plaque.
And so dextran
allows for cells to
begin to stick and
create that plaque
biofilm in your
mouth on your teeth.
Now, in the same way that
dextran is going to allow
for dental plaque biofilm
production, that's the
same way that dextran is
going to mediate vegetation
to grow on a disrupted
heart valve. And so the
viridens family is going to
be the most common cause of
subacute infective
endocarditis. And so that's kind
of a key point to make
sure that you understand.
So whenever you are thinking
about some sort of dental
procedure, that's going
to allow for these types
of bacteria, the viridens
group, to gain access to
the blood after some sort
of manipulation or procedure
in your mouth. and that
especially in the background
of endocarditis is then
going to be a subacute
case all right so being
able to understand that is
important all right the
second example is um strep
galliliticus now galliliticus
is a newer designation
a newer name for this
species it used to be called
strep bovis and strep
bovis or strep galliliticus
is typically an inhabitant
of the GI tract in humans.
And so, like you can see
in the chart, when you
find gallilliticus in the
bloodstream, right, or bovis
in the blood, you should
start to think cancer in
the colon. So it's a little
mnemonic device to use.
So the presence of
strep gallilliticus in
the bloodstream is very,
very strongly associated
with polyps in the
colon, colon cancer,
neoplasms in the
colon. So if that
is identified, there
would certainly be
a need to follow
up with a colonoscopy
after that.
All right. So strep
galliiticus is a little bit
different than the viridens
group because it does get
grouped into a Lansfield
grouping, which is group D.
And you can see that the
enterococcus group is also
group D, right? So you
have both enterococcus and
streptococcus falling into
this Lansfield grouping.
All right, so the
question then becomes, how
do you begin to
differentiate these different
types of streps? And
you're going to be
considering different
biochemical features.
So if we then take
a catalase positive
coccus, gram positive
coccus, I'm sorry, a
catalase negative coccus,
then what we could
do is assume that it's
going to be a strep.
And at that point, we
want to differentiate the
viridin's streps from the
other possibilities. And so you
would do that with a bile
escaline test. The bile
escaline test is asking the
question, can the bacteria
hydrolyze escaline? in the
medium and so on the slide
you can see a bioescaline
tube that is negative
where the medium is kind
of an orangey yellow color
that's how it starts and if the
escaline is being hydrolyzed
that'll convert the
medium to a black color so
black would be a positive
test for that so very quick
easy way of distinguishing
the group d from the
viridens group with a
bioescaline test But if the strep
and the enterococcus
groupings are both Escaline
positive, then how are we
going to differentiate those?
So the enterococcus,
which is also a normal
inhabitant of the
human flora, so you
can find that also
in the GI tract. You
can find that in the
female genital tract.
So you would consider
enterococcus as
being a cause after
some sort of procedure,
right, a genital or
gastrointestinal procedure,
allowing that to gain
access to the blood.
All right, so how do we
begin differentiating
those? And what you can
consider are basically two
different biochemical
features of the species.
So number one, the ability
to grow in a high salt
environment. So Enterococcus
typically is capable of
growing at high salt
concentrations, whereas the Strep
galliiticus is not. But probably
a more key distinguishing
biochemical feature
is going to be the PYR
test, where the Enterococcus
species is going to be
positive for the PYR test.
The Strep galliiticus species
is going to be negative
for the PYR test. So if
you're in a situation where
you have a catalase negative
positive coccus and your
bile escalin positive as
well, right, that's putting
you into the group D
category, if you see PYR
positive, you automatically know
that you're talking about
an anorecoccus species.
ways that you're
going to be able to
differentiate the
strep species and the
anorecoccus species
one from the other as a
potential causative
agent of endocarditis.
All right, so now that we've
covered the staph and the
strep groups, what we've
done is covered approximately
two-thirds of the most
common causative agents of
IE. So what we're going to
do is transition now to the
less common atypical causative
agents of endocarditis.
And what I've done
is separated them
into two groups based
on gram reaction.
So we have the gram
positives and the
gram negatives
presented here. So
we'll start with
the gram positives.
The first gram positive
example is, of course, another
strep, even though I said
that we've covered the
strep group already. but
a little bit different
here. So this is a nutritionally
variant strep known
as NVS. So when you consider
NVS, it is part of the
normal oral flora. And
what you would want to do
is identify this as similar
to a viridens type of
species, a viridens strep
species. And so it is going
to have the same portal
of entry. You want to
consider some sort of oral
trauma or oral procedure
that's going to allow it to
get into the bloodstream.
But the only difference
with NVS is the fact that it
doesn't readily grow. You
can't readily culture it. And
the reason for that is because
it's basically a mutant.
It's a nutritional mutant
and it doesn't have the
ability to synthesize pyridoxal.
And pyridoxal is basically
a version of B6. So that
would have to be supplemented
into the medium that you
were using to grow NVS.
Now, another kind of
unique aspect to NVS is the
fact that it will produce
satellite colonies around
other bacterial species,
such as Staph aureus.
And the reason for that
is that species like Staph
aureus will actually
secrete nutrients into their
environment like pyridoxal,
and that will then allow for
the strep species to grow
in that local environment.
All right, now the second
example here is known
as Carinibacterium, which
is a genus of bacteria.
So Carinibacterium is,
again, a normal inhabitant,
normal flora for humans
found on the skin. It's
found in the upper
respiratory tract. And
Carinibacterium, in terms of
the species, are oftentimes
just categorized as what's
known as diphtheroids.
So that relates really to
the shapes of the cells.
So the cells themselves
are not necessarily
uniform like you would
expect from other species,
although they are considered
rods. They're not perfectly
straight, uniform-looking
rods, but instead,
oftentimes, they're bent,
and so they're said to be
club-shaped when you see
them under a microscope.
Now, if this is going
to be associated with
endocarditis, it's typically
going to be from some
sort of contamination
event with a prosthetic
device a prosthetic
valve something like that
if you wanted to grow
coronibacterium you can culture
it on a number of different
media but if you really
want to isolate it on its
own and enrich it you would
want to in a laboratory
setting use a medium known as
loffler's medium instead
all right now the last
example that we're taking a
look at in the gram positive
group is another gram
positive rod known as listeria
listeria monocytogenes
and listeria is a very
well-known foodborne
pathogen and it is unique
because it has the
capability of growing at
refrigerator temperatures
and so typically
it's going to be a
foodborne pathogen that's
associated typically
with dairy products
Specifically,
unpasteurized cheeses
would be a good example
of how you could get
a listeria infection.
And usually it's going
to affect typically the
elderly, young individuals,
and certainly pregnant
individuals as well. So listeria
also is kind of uniquely
a facultative intracellular
pathogen. So it has
the ability to inhabit
macrophages and monocytes.
All right, so those are
some of the gram-positive,
atypical gram-positives
that you would want to be
aware of. Now we'll
transition here to the gram
-negative group. And the
first gram-negative group to
talk about really is truly
a group of bacteria known
as the Hossic bacteria.
And so the term HOSIC is an
acronym, and the acronym
comes from the five
different genera of bacteria
that fit into the group. So
you can see them listed
in the chart on the side,
Haemophilus, Actinobacillus,
Cardiobacterium, Iconella,
and Kingella. So that makes
up the acronym. Now, it's
worth mentioning that the
first two, Haemophilus and
Actinobacillus, those have
been recategorized into a
different genus, which is
known as Aggregated Bacter,
but the Hossack
designation has not
changed because of
that genus change.
So, when you consider
the Hossack bacteria, the
Hossack bacteria are very
similar to the Viridin
strep group because they
are part of the normal
oral flora again. The
difference being that
these are gram-negative
bacilli as opposed to being
gram-positive cocci,
like the streps would be.
And these are a little
bit different in terms
of the fact that they
are slow-growing, right?
A little bit more
difficult to culture in
comparison to what the
strep species would be.
But because they are part
of the normal flora, again,
very similar to the NVS
that we just talked about,
You would want to consider,
again, dental procedures,
some sort of oral trauma
as being the portal of
entry into the bloodstream
for these. And so in terms
of different pathogens that
have the ability to cause
endocarditis, the Hossack
organisms are positioned
as the most common cause of
gram-negative endocarditis
in patients that specifically
don't use IV drugs.
So if you are an individual
that has endocarditis
and does use IV drugs,
then the most common gram
-negative cause would be
the pathogen Pseudomonas.
So
we'll stick with the
gram-negative bacteria
here and give a few
more examples of
culture-negative
microbes that cause IE,
specifically Coxiella,
Legionella, and Bartonella.
Now, these microbes
get grouped up together
because when subject to
the gram stain procedure,
none of them gram stain
particularly well, even
though they all are
considered to be gram negative
microbes. So in addition
to gram staining,
oftentimes other staining
procedures have to be
utilized, like silver
staining or game sustaining,
in addition to other
methods of identification
like serological
testing or PCR analysis.
All right, so the first
one in the group is
coxiella bernetii, and
coxiella is a little bit
unique insofar as it is
an obligate intracellular
pathogen, so this
would be a very good
candidate for serological
testing or PCR analysis,
depending on the stage
of the infection.
Now, it's also worth
pointing out that coxiella
is the most common cause
of culture-negative
endocarditis. So that's
something that you would want
to keep in mind about the
culture negative group.
All right, the second on
the list is Legionella.
Legionella is categorized
as a fastidious organism. So
it's actually extremely
fastidious, very difficult to
grow because it has pretty
strict nutritional needs.
So you can't just
culture it on any old
media. You need very
specific media like BCYE
and it isn't very easy
to culture in a lab.
And the last one on
the list is Bartonella.
Now Bartonella is
the genus name,
so different species
could be the cause of
endocarditis. So Bartonella
henselae or Bartonella
quintana, both of which
are going to cause
independent pathologies
themselves. And actually
all of these examples
of microbes are going
to to cause independent
diseases on their own.
But so Bartonella
is very similar to
Listeria like we talked
about insofar as it
is a facultative
intracellular pathogen.
All right now that
we covered the main
bacterial causes what
I want to do is just
revisit and summarize
some of the virulence
factors associated
with those groups.
So when you think about
virulence factors you
could basically subdivide
them into two different
broad categories, like
you see on the slide
here. So the first is going
to be immune resistance,
and the second is
going to be adherence.
All right, so in terms of
immune resistance, you would
imagine that the bacteria
that are going to be
causing endocarditis have
to make their way from their
standard location to the
heart, right? So they have to
have a way to get from the
oral cavity to the heart.
If you're, let's say, using
a needle in your arm, there
has to be a way to get from
your arm to your heart.
And so that requires
that the bacteria move
through the bloodstream.
And once you're in
the bloodstream, you
are now subject to
being identified by the
host immune response.
and that could be either
proteins of the innate
response or it can be
phagocytes associated with the
innate response. And so
the main way that bacteria
are going to prevent being
identified is going to
be by producing a capsule.
Now not all capsules are
the same but many different
varieties and species
of bacteria make capsules.
So for instance we already
talked about capsule
formation in staph aureus.
All right, so staph aureus
produces a capsule, and
that really is specifically
for host immune evasion,
not necessarily for
adherence, in addition to
the coagulase that it
secretes and the fibrin shield
that it makes, so kind
of a secondary way that
it's shielding itself
from being identified by
complement proteins or
different types of thagocytes.
But Staph aureus is not
the only bacteria that does
that. So, you know, you could
put in the same category,
Enarococcus faecalis will
produce a capsule to evade
the host immune response.
So too do some of the
Hossic bacterial species
produce capsules. So you could
see that it's kind of a
common way that you could
defend yourself against
the host immune response.
all right now once you get
to where you're going you
have to have a way of sticking
to that or adhering to
the heart valve and so the
second category of virulence
factors in terms of
endocarditis is going to be
what is actually allowing
the microbe to stick to the
heart valve or the pre
-existing thrombus that is
located at that site and so
here you could actually put
capsule formation in this
category as well, right?
So, you might recall
when we talked about the
staph group, we talked
about staph, the other
staph, staph epidermidis,
also producing a capsule.
Now, the capsule that
it produces is a little
bit different than the
capsule that staph aureus
would produce. The capsule
that staph epi produces
is more constructed
like a slime layer, And
that allows for adherence
to abiotic substrates,
right? So staph epidermidis
can then begin creating
biofilms on devices, right?
So indwelling catheters,
prosthetic joints, or
heart valves, right? So
the capsule in that
situation is going to allow
for adherence and for the
development of biofilm.
now in terms of the streps
right so you can see
the first two points in
adherence relate to the strep
group so first is going to
be the dextran secretion
of the viridens group
right so if you remember
the strep viridens group
is going to be typically
found in the oral cavity
and the dextran secretion
is going to be utilized
for the creation of
plaque biofilm right which
is essentially an adherence
property of the dextran
creating that biofilm.
And of course, the secretion
of dextran in the heart,
right, on a heart valve on
a pre-existing thrombus is
going to allow for attachment
and adherence in very
much the same way that it
happens in the oral cavity.
In addition to that, there
is a protein that some of
those species have, some of
the strep viridin species,
which is known as FIM
-A. So FIM-A is a surface
protein that is going to
allow for adhesion to a pre
-existing thrombus and will
serve essentially the same
function as dextran, just
for allowing the strep to
adhere. Now FIM-A is not
specific to strep, but in
terms of our or talk about
endocarditis, you could
pair it up with being a
strep viridins-based protein.
All right, now the last point
about adherence is really
specific to staph aureus.
And if you remember,
staph aureus is really the
main causative agent of IE.
And not only can it
create a subacute case in
very specific circumstances,
right, with a pre-existing
thrombus or damage to
a heart valve. But staph
aureus is the main cause of
acute endocarditis. And the
reason for that is because
of its virulence factors.
So we already talked
about its immune resistance,
right, the host resistance,
the capsule formation,
secretion of coagulase,
right, those are going to
be virulence factors that
allow it to persist in the
blood and not be cleared by
the immune system. But it
also has the ability to
bind to the endothelial
cells of the heart valves,
specifically healthy heart
valves. And so this is what
produces acute cases. And
this is what makes staph
aureus so virulent, right,
and why you get an acute
case occurring with pathology
over only a few days.
So staph aureus will produce
surface-level binding
proteins, which are
fibronectin, called fibronectin
binding proteins, in
addition to a variation of
coagulase known as clumping
factors. So clumping factor
is yet another surface
-level protein used for
adhesion. And so those proteins
have the ability to bind
to receptor proteins on
endothelial cells, healthy
endothelial cells, especially
if those endothelial
cells might be undergoing
some minor inflammation,
upregulating surface-level
proteins like integrins,
maybe secreting fibronectin.
You have the perfect
situation then for staph
aureus to exploit binding
to a healthy the endothelial
cell, and by doing that,
then it can create the
environment to not only enter
into the cell, right,
tissue destruction, really
damage the heart valve,
but then to begin creating
from scratch the vegetation
that is commonly seen
with an infection, an
endocarditis infection.
All
right, so we've discussed
many of the bacterial
causes of IE, as well
as reviewed some of
the virulence factors
associated with them.
So now we're going to take
a quick look at the fungal
causes of endocarditis. And
generally speaking, it's
pretty rare to have a
fungus causing endocarditis.
And generally, it will be
secondary to some sort of
invasive heart procedure or
secondary to IV drug use.
And you can see some of the
stats associated with that
on the slide. So upwards
of 15% of endocarditis
associated with prosthetic
valves would be fungal origin.
And 20%, up to 20% of
endocarditis associated with IV
drug use would have a fungal
origin as well. Now, the
fungi that can cause this,
certainly the most common
fungi that can cause this
are candida and aspergillus.
So candida is a yeast,
basically meaning that it's
more of a cell-like structure,
whereas aspergillus is
a mold. So molds tend to
grow in filamentous networks
that are called hyphae. And
on the side of the slide,
you can see images of both
of those fungi. So the
top image is a microscopic
view of candida albicans.
Now, we just said that it's
a yeast, and it certainly
looks like there's filaments
in that image. So this
is pretty diagnostic for
candida. It grows and creates
what's known as pseudohyphae.
So it looks like
filaments, but really the
cells have elongated, and
after budding, they fail to
detach from one another and
so it gives the appearance
of hyphae but they're not
true hyphae the bottom image
is aspergillus and this
is a view of only part of
it so the part that you're
looking at is technically
modified hyphae which are
the reproductive structures
known as conidiophores
conidiophores are going
to terminate in this fan
-like structure that houses
the conidia which are
the spores and then allows
for their dispersion so
those are the two main
causes of fungal endocarditis
so candida and aspergillus
but of course there's
some atypical forms as
well like you see listed
below so coccidioides
histoplasma or cryptococcus
all right so let's start
putting this together
a little bit more clinically
and diagnostically
so to have ie you need
basically two different
things occurring so number
one you need transient
bacteria in the bloodstream
and so the first
thing that you want to
start thinking about is how
did that get there how
would the what's the
portal of entry right for
your particular patient
So here's certainly a
non-exhaustive list,
but you might want to
start considering, well,
did my patient have
some sort of oral trauma
recently or maybe some
planned dental procedure?
So if that's the case,
maybe you want to start
thinking maybe the strep
viridens group, right?
Maybe the Hossack bacteria,
if my culture is not
growing all that well,
maybe NBS in that case.
does my patient have an
indwelling vascular device if
that's the case well now I
already know that there's
a direct portal of entry
into the bloodstream so does
my patient abuse IV drugs
right and in that case there's
a strong association with
right-sided endocarditis
specifically with the
tricuspid valve and if you have
that particular risk factor
well then you could start
to assume what might be
the causative agent behind
that infection. So the most
common in that case would
be Staph aureus, right? I
guess Staph aureus would be
the most common in most
cases, followed by Candida,
right? The fungus that we
just talked about. And then
Pseudomonas, which is a
gram-negative bacillus. So
Pseudomonas oftentimes is
very difficult to treat and is
very associated with IV
drug use as a risk category.
So you have to have some
sort of transient microbe in
the bloodstream. And of
course, now, in addition to
that, you need some sort of
disruption of the endothelium,
right, of a heart valve.
And so you need the
formation or the beginning
of a formation of a thrombus.
So you need some place for
those microbes to locate.
And so you need the
development of the thrombus,
this aggregate of fibrin
and thrombin and platelets
coming together, allowing
for a surface for which the
bacteria can adhere to. And
once that happens, you begin
to increase the microbial
population by division.
Of course, that's
going to recruit
immune proteins to
the location, too.
And so you get this ever
-expanding vegetation
in the area, which is
going to lead to then the
disruption of the valve
and how it functions.
So that can happen in most
of the valves, right, in
the heart. but certainly
is going to occur most
frequently on the left side
of the heart. So the mitral
valve is going to be the
one that is going to be
affected the most in most
cases, right, followed by the
aortic valve. So when you
think infected endocarditis,
you really want to think
left side of the heart.
For the tricuspid valve
right at the right side
of the heart, of course,
we just talked about the
association with the IV
drug use risk category.
So that's really going
to be the primary time
when you're going to assume
that you'll have right
-sided, i.e., and very
infrequently, are you
going to have involvement
with the pulmonic valve.
So what are some
of the signs and
symptoms we should be aware of?
Well, first, we have this
wonderful acronym from Jane.
And the first part of
that is probably the most
common. So you have a
patient that has a fever, a
fever and a new heart
murmur, right? So now you
would imagine that in
the patient, you have a
pretty significant inflammatory
response occurring.
And the cytokines that
are bringing about
that inflammatory
response are responsible
for the fever, but
also responsible for
some of the systemic
symptoms that you see.
So, you know, other things like
malaise and fatigue
and weight loss.
Now some of the other signs
that you see there are
represented in the images
so the first is known as
Roth spots which are
associated with the retina. So
this is going to be due to
small micro septic emboli
that are going to cause
hemorrhaging in the retina
and the hemorrhages have
a classic central clearing
a little white spot like
you can see in the image.
now septic emboli are going
to be responsible also
for some of the other
signs that are associated
with ie like janeway lesions
and so this is where you
get emboli that are
targeting the small blood
vessels of the hands or
the feet leading to small
hemorrhagic lesions like
you can see in the image and
emboli are also going to
be responsible for splinter
hemorrhages that are then
going to be targeting
the capillaries of the
nail bed now the one that i
skipped over the osler
node is not necessarily due
to septic emboli but
instead is due to the immune
system response to
circulating bacterial antigens
so this is essentially a
hypersensitivity reaction
leading to immune
complex deposition in the
location where you find
this tender lesion the
Osler node, generally in
the fingers or the toes.
Now, you would imagine
that that's not just
happening in those
locations, but can happen
elsewhere in the body
as well. And so one very
documented complication
of IE is something
known as glomerulonephritis,
where you have
deposition of immune
complexes in the kidney and
then subsequent
inflammation because of it.
so the system for diagnosing
ie follows the major and
minor duke criteria and the
combinations of them you
could see presented on the
slide now the minor criteria
relate to some of the
things that we've talked
about already right so things
like risk factors or some
of the signs and symptoms
that we just talked about.
And the major
criteria relate to
either blood
cultures or imaging.
Now, in terms of blood
cultures, it's really important
to understand whether
your patient has had
antibiotic treatment or else
there is the potential for
having killed off the
bacteria prior to the culture.
And the imaging is
going to be accomplished
by an echocardiogram.
So that would either be
a transthoracic echocardiogram
or a transesophageal
echocardiogram,
which would give you
a little bit better
resolution of the valves.
So the following
questions are for your
individual review, and the
answers can be found in
the notes section of
the PowerPoint slides.
So that concludes the
lecture. I just wanted
to thank everyone
for listening, and I
wanted to provide the
link for feedback.